<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The New test of the Church of England's loyalty, examined by the old test of truth and honesty</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N781</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7988</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12990844</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12990844</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96337</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70712)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96337)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 393:17 or 946:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The New test of the Church of England's loyalty, examined by the old test of truth and honesty</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.G.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing reel guide incorrectly refers to item as N782.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library and Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96337:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96337:1"/>
            <p>THE New TEST OF THE Church of England's LOYALTY, Examined by the Old TEST OF Truth and Honeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. G.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96337:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96337:2"/>
            <head>THE NEW TEST OF THE Church of England's LOYALTY, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE reaſon why the Church of <hi>England</hi> may above any Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts from her appropriate to her ſelf the Principles of true Loyalty, is ſo apparent from her conſtant Practiſe and Doctrin, that one would think this Scribler <hi>of the New Teſt</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſidered it at all (though he tells us he hath often conſider'd) becauſe he cannot find it. For I challenge him or any man to ſhew me any that are not of her Communion (not excluding even <hi>the Calves of the Hind,</hi> the Sons of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf) that did conſtantly maintain the Doctrin of Non-reſiſtance to the Supream Magiſtrate and practiſe according to it; as our Church and her true Sons have always done. Was there ever any ſuch Doctrin as the Depoſing of Kings, the ſubjecting them to a foreign Biſhop, or to an Aſſembly at home, the making them Truſtees of the People, or aſcribing an Authority Co-ordinate to theirs in the Peoples Repreſentatives, the founding Dominion in Grace; or Laſtly, owning a Power in the inferiour Magiſtrates to Act without, or contrary to their Commiſſion taught by our Loyal Mother: and have not ſome or all of theſe been taught by ſome of the other Parties? So that if they are Loyal it is no thanks to their Religion for it. Have not all the other Parties acted accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96337:3"/>to theſe Antimonarchical principles? Or can the worſt of our Enemies with any truth accuſe our Church or her true Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of any ſuch Actions? But, <hi>what</hi> (ſaith this Teſt-maker) <hi>can be more ridiculous then for ſuch, who cannot pretend to infallibility even in matters of Faith, to aſſume to themſelves an inerrability in civil Obedience?</hi> Oh profound Senſe and Reaſon! what cannot Men be Loyal, and Act according to their conſtant Principles of Loyalty without being infallible? Or will not this Gentleman give us leave to be ſo kind to him, or any of the Members of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as to think them indued with Loyalty without robbing their Holy Father the <hi>Pope</hi> of his Prerogative of Infallibility, and aſcribing part to his Sons? Did ever any Man of the Church of <hi>England</hi> aſſume to himſelf <hi>an inerrability in his Obedience;</hi> onely ſo long as he kept cloſe to his Rule his Church hath given him? I am ſure on the contrary, the Sons of that Church that aſſumes to her ſelf Infallibilty in matters of Faith, can never be indued with <hi>that ſingular Gift of Loyalty,</hi> ſo long as they keep themſelves out of the reach of the <hi>Anathema</hi> of their infallible Council of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran,</hi> affix'd by an <hi>inerrable Canon upon all ſuch as deny the Pope's power to depoſe Heretical Princes or Favourers of</hi> Hereticks. So that I muſt needs own (if they are Loyal) their Loyalty far exceeds ours, ſince they are Loyal at the peril of their immortal Souls, whereas we can only venture our Temporal concerns for our Prince.</p>
            <p>If therefore you will ſhew your ſelves truly Loyal, in the next Addreſs renounce that diſloyal Canon of the Council of <hi>Lateran;</hi> or elſe we muſt believe either, that you are not Catholicks (as in your Religion, you love to be called) or elſe do but ſerve a turn in your Pretences of Loyalty.</p>
            <p>Out of his abundant kindneſs to the Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> this Gentleman is pleaſed to allow them to have been <hi>Faithful and Serviceable to King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt;</hi> we are extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obliged to him for this ſo favourable a Conceſſion; and indeed I could not but have ſome thoughts of preſenting an Addreſs of thanks to him for it: But that he hath ſaved me the trouble in ſo well explaining it. For he tells us, that this was only <hi>in our own defence, and not joyning with the common Enemy to cut our own Throats;</hi> nay further, <hi>that the Ambition of our Church occaſion'd the late War, and the loſs of the King's Life and Crown.</hi> If ſo; then our Church
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96337:3"/>was ſerviceable to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt with a vengeance. This (me thinks) looks ſomething like a <hi>Dear-joye's Witticiſm,</hi> or in plain Engliſh a down-right Bull, that we ſhould be <hi>ſerviceable to our King,</hi> and yet, <hi>occaſion the loſs of his Crown and Life:</hi> But it is no matter what Contradictions he writes, if he can but thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatter the Church of <hi>England;</hi> he knows he is to deal with a People of an implicit Faith that can ſwallow any Contradictions, or falſe Stories. Did ever any Man thus out-face the Sun as he hath done in theſe Aſperſions? Do not all Men (that know any thing of the Hiſtory of the late times) know that if we of the Church of <hi>England</hi> would have joyn'd with the Rebels, or, but have owned the Uſurpers Authority, we might have enjoyed all our Rites, and have expected much greater Preferments? Was not this then very like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting our own preſent Intereſt to ſuffer Sequeſtrations, Decimations, Plunderings, Impriſonments; nay Death it ſelf, rather then Act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Duty to our Prince? Is it not as viſible as the Sun, that the firſt pretence for the late War was for ſecuring of Property, and that Religion was but made a ſtalking Horſe to catch the Rabble? How then was <hi>the Ambition of our Church, the occaſion of it?</hi> But, Oh the admirable Loyalty of the <hi>Romaniſts, That ſerved the King without any Prpſpect of advantage to themſelves; Nay, when their Services were rejected by the King, and their Perſons baniſhed from his Preſence!</hi> Did not the Rebellious party cry out againſt Popery, and pretend that they only deſigned to ſecure the Nation againſt <hi>Papiſts?</hi> they knew, or at leaſt at firſt believed (as he ſaith) they ſhould meet <hi>with no quarter from the Rebels,</hi> and therefore where ſhould they fly for ſafety, to the Royal party? but as ſoon as His Majeſty was forced by his Parliament to diſcard them, and that they ſaw the other party would receive them, how many of them Liſted themſelves under their Banners? <hi>And,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. the Works of K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr. fol. 323.</note> 
               <hi>All Men know the great numbers of Papiſts which ſerve in their (the Rebells) Army, Commanders and others;</hi> and hath not Old <hi>Peter Du Moulin</hi> long ſince aſſerted, and offered to prove it by undoubted Evidence, that a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> at the very execution of his late Majeſty K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, was ſeen amongſt the Rebels <hi>throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his Cap for Joy;</hi> inſulting in the moſt barbarous manner over that poor Prince in his laſt Tragick Exit? So true is it, <hi>That never any of that Communion ſerved that Party.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This infallible Author is reſolved he will do the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s buſineſs for Loyalty, and therefore he rakes up all the odious
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96337:4"/>Acts that ever have been done, ſince the <hi>infancy</hi> of our Church (as he words it, <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>in fine</hi>) and very obligingly fathers them upon her. Of all which the <hi>Scotch</hi> Anſwer, <hi>viz. Bellarmine thou lyeſt</hi> is a ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation.</p>
            <p>For as for that, that <hi>ſhe</hi> [the Church of <hi>England</hi>] <hi>endeavoured with all her might to ſet up a Brat of her own to exclude Queen</hi> Mary. It is ſo void of all appearance of Truth, that it would puzzle any man by the Hiſtory of thoſe Times to gueſs what he means by it. I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he means the Lady <hi>Jane Gray.</hi> But was not ſhe ſet up by the Ambition of <hi>Dudley</hi> D. of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> who thereby hoped to have raiſed his Family [his Son being her Husband] to the Royal Dignity? Did not the Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who were then in <hi>Power</hi> joyn againſt him? Nay did not <hi>Northumberland</hi> himſelf after he was taken [ſo true a Son of our Church he was] offer to embrace the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to ſave his Life? Was it not eaſy for the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> at that time to have ſet up her Siſter <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whom they knew to be of their own Religion, and to have excluded Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> but ſo far were they from oppoſing the right Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that upon her Arrival into <hi>Framingam-Caſtle,</hi> they readily joyned with her, and ſet her upon her Throne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But after Queen</hi> Mary's <hi>Death,</hi> (ſaith he ibid.) <hi>Elizabeth a known Baſtard raiſed the Church of</hi> England <hi>as a Prop to ſupport the Weakneſs of her Title.</hi> Is not this ſaid like a true Loyal Jeſuit, ſhewing the Honour he hath for Crown'd Heads, by fixing upon one of the moſt renown'd of them, the moſt Honourable Title of a plain, downright Baſtard? Nay, it is by ſo much more like him, by how much it wants of Truth. Was not Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth born in Wedlock after a moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Divorce, grounded upon one of the juſteſt Cauſes that could be, <hi>viz.</hi> The Nullity of his former Marriage with the Lady <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> of <hi>Spain?</hi> Was not it thought at firſt ſo by Cardinal <hi>Wolſey,</hi> nay, by the Pope himſelf, who had he not been overaw'd by the Emperour, would have determined the Marriage unlawful, nay, did not he ſign a Bull to that purpoſe? I dare appeal to this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman himſelf, whether there be not far more Reaſon to believe it unlawful for a Man to Marry his Brother's Wife, than there is to think it Lawful? Now if this Queſtion muſt be determined in the Aſſirmative, doth it not directly follow that Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Legitimacy was far more uncertain, and conſequently her Title did
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96337:4"/>more need <hi>a Prop to ſupport the Weakneſs of it,</hi> than her Siſter Queen <hi>Elizabeth's? Henry</hi> the Eighth their Father knew this well enough, and therefore ſettled the matter (as well as he could) by Acts of Parliament; which right I ſhall not diſpute. But however if the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> thought it good againſt the <hi>Scotch</hi> title for Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> why might not the Proteſtants think it as good for Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth? But they</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>no ſooner found themſelves ſo eſtabliſhed, then they fell to making thoſe Canibal-Laws to Hang, Draw, and Quarter the Prieſts of the Living God,</hi> &amp;c. Not ſo faſt, I beſeech you Sir, were theſe Edicts made or conſented to by the Convocation? were theſe ever made Canons of our Church? Why then is not the Saddle ſet upon the right Horſe, and they own'd to be the acts of State, and not of our Church? Again, how can theſe be ſaid to be true <hi>Prieſts of the Living God,</hi> who would not own the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that God had ſet over us in our Nation, but look'd upon the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate, as one depoſed by the Popes Authority, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged to Death, and therefore were continually Plotting and Contriving againſt her Life and Dignity, and ſetting up the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> Title againſt her, which forced the Queen and her Council (which had it not been neceſſary, I am ſure the Members of our Church would have thought moſt inhumane) to take away the Life of that unfortunate Princeſs? Now I pray what Crime is it, or what fault is it in our Church, if the Supream Power of our Nation does enact Laws to ſecure the Government? Or what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty is it for the Church of <hi>England</hi> not to join with Rebells, or for the State to puniſh them by Law?</p>
            <p>Oh! but <hi>theſe Laws are exclaimed againſt by all the Reformed Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Chriſtendom,</hi> &amp;c. (p. 5.) But for this we muſt only take this Gentleman's bare word; of the Sincerity of which, this Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plet hath already given us ſuch undoubted Inſtances as cannot but prevail with us, if we reſolve never to be believ'd our ſelves, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him; but ſuppoſing any of the Reformed ſhould ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, have not our Governours the Power of determining by Law what is neceſſary for the publick Peace?</p>
            <p>But however who can endure to hear Papiſts crying up Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and exclaiming againſt Sanguinary Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For, this is for the Kettle to accuſe the Pot of Blackneſs. Who I pray firſt enacted <hi>that Act, De Heretico Comburendo,</hi> and as long as they had Power, nay ſometimes, (as in the Caſe of <hi>John Huſſe,</hi> &amp;c.)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96337:5"/>contrary to the moſt ſolemn Promiſe of an whole Council of their Clergy) put it in Execution?</p>
            <p>Who was it that found out that old meek Method of convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hereticks by the <hi>Inquiſition?</hi> or that more Harmleſs way (now ſo much celebrated by the French Clergy) of perſwading them by <hi>Booted Apoſtles,</hi> who will neither let them <hi>Fly,</hi> nor <hi>Dye,</hi> nor Sleep, nor Eat in quiet, till they have own'd their Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            <p>Who was it that Muthered ſuch numbers of the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> in cold Blood, in the days of <hi>Yore,</hi> and in latter times butchered ſo many Thouſands of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſince that put to the Sword ſo many Proteſtants about <hi>Piedmont?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who was it that murthered two Princes one after another, <hi>viz. Henry</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and raiſed that Bloody League, called the Holy League (a pattern to our Proteſtant-Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its-<hi>Scotch</hi>-Covenant) by which ſo many Thouſands were deſtroyed by War? Who was it that approved theſe things, and made Panegyrick Orations upon them? Were theſe Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> I leave it to this Gentleman to tell us in his next Pamphlet, if he deſires to hear any more of theſe matters: and ſhall conclude this affair with an Expreſſion of his own rightly applyed, <hi>viz. That if Murtherers of their Lawful Soveraigns; if making holy Leagues againſt them; if raiſing Wars and Commotions in all Kingdoms; and Canons of Infallible General Councils that bind them to ſuch Actions under an Anathema be ſufficient Teſtimenies of Loyalty, we muſt own the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>to have been hitherto unparallel'd in her Duty, but if this be not the true Teſt of Loyal Subjects, our Rock of Loyalty is already degenerate into a Rock of Scandal, of Deſobedience, and Rebellion.</hi> p. 5, in fine &amp; p. 6.</p>
            <p>The reſt of his Diſcourſe from <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>line the 7th.</hi> is taken up in baſe and falſe Inſinuations of the <hi>Church of England's Diſloyalty,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>Ingratitude</hi> to our preſent King, in that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Gracious Promiſes and Royal Word to maintain our Religion, we dare not truſt him, nor had not ſo much Gratitude to take off the <hi>Sanguinary Laws and the Teſt</hi> at his requeſt.</p>
            <p>But (Good Sir) if our <hi>Parliament of England</hi> will not do this, what is it to the <hi>Church of England?</hi> Why muſt the Church anſwer for the Acts of the State? or why is it Ingratitude or Diſloyalty to ſecure our ſelves againſt Popiſh Prieſts who hold
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96337:5"/>
               <hi>there is no Faith to be kept with us,</hi> and teach this Doctrine to all ſorts of Perſons? Why (I pray you) is it not more Ingratitude and Diſloyalty in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to a Prince that hath been ſo prodigiouſly kind to her, to venture theſe Kingdoms for her ſake, not to take off that <hi>Bull</hi> that hinders them from Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating with the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and <hi>Pius Quartus</hi> his <hi>Creed,</hi> and the Injunction of Subſcribing to it, which would go very far in Uniting the two Churches? If this be not ingratitude in her ſtill to keep her Poſt, why is it in the Church of <hi>England</hi> to do the ſame? Let us ſee the Pope and Clergy of <hi>Rome</hi> ſet us this Example of Gratitude, and this may be a great inducement to our Church and Nation to follow it. Suppoſe a Man hath good flights of Pidgeons in his Dove-houſe, and loves them well, and therefore hath provided ſuch a Trap as he hath experienc'd, does keep out the Vermin, that otherwiſe would creep in and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his Pidgeons, would you not think him a Mad man, or elſe very willing to ſuffer his innocent Doves to be utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed that ſhould take away his Trap, and thereby give leave to all the devouring <hi>Weezles, Polcats, Hawks, Owles, Buzzards, and Carrion-crows</hi> to come in amongſt them and not only diſturb, but deſtroy them at their pleaſure?</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Teſt</hi> be ſo Ungrateful and Diſloyal a thing to our Church, why is not the <hi>Teſt</hi> in <hi>France</hi> (which was a Pattern to ours, nay, doth far exceed it, for the Right Heir to the Crown is excluded there without taking it) a greater ſign of Ingratitude and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty in the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this <hi>Teſt was contrived by</hi> Shafsbury <hi>and deſign'd againſt the King himſelf.</hi> (ibid. p. 6.)</p>
            <p>Was it ſo? why then do you throw it upon the Church of <hi>England?</hi> is the Church of <hi>England</hi> to anſwer for <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions who was her greateſt Enemy? but however (to give the Devil his due) how can this <hi>Teſt</hi> be deſign'd againſt the King, when the Royal Family are particularly exempted from taking it; which was on purpoſe ſo contriv'd by the Loyal Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Parliament to ſecure <hi>the Succeſſion in a right Line?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Houſe of Commons <hi>made an Adreſs to his Majeſty, that none ſhould be Employed, who were not capacitated by the ſaid Laws and Teſt.</hi> (i.e.) in ſhort; <hi>Your Majeſty muſt have none either in the Army, or as Court, but ſuch as really believe, and will ſwear to it, that you are an Idolater;</hi> Theſe are his words, <hi>ibid. p.</hi> 6.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96337:6"/>
            <p>Why in the firſt place, <hi>ſuch as will ſwear,</hi> &amp;c. The Oaths that are required by the <hi>Teſt,</hi> are only the Oaths of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</hi> Now why any ſhould be truſted with the Power of the Nation, who will not ſwear Fealty to the Government, my dull Politicks I confeſs cannot underſtand. As for the renouncing of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> a bare Declaration and Subſcription <hi>without Swearing</hi> is all that the <hi>Teſt</hi> it ſelf doth command. But this it is for a Man to write (as he believes) by an implicit Faith <hi>(i.e.)</hi> to take things upon Truſt without any Examination, and to ſet them down for Truths.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe now the worſt that can be, that it was Literally true as he would have it. What harm would it be to <hi>his Majeſty, to be ſerved by none but ſuch as believe, and will ſwear that he is an Idolater;</hi> if they are all ſuch (as the Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) <hi>who do believe and think themſelves bound to ſerve him faithfully, though he really was not only an Idolater, but an Heathen?</hi> Is he not far ſafer in ſuch hands, than in the hands of ſuch, who though they think him not an Idolater, yet if they think him an Heretick, or a favourer of Hereticks, may think themſelves bound to deſtroy him; eſpecially if a Foreign Power ſhall give them Authority, as too many Popes have done, even againſt thoſe Princes that have profeſſed the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion? Laſtly, who is there of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that becauſe he himſelf doth not believe Tranſubſtantiation, does therefore think that the King does not? or that will pronounce him an Idolater for Worſhiping that which he believes is God?</p>
            <p>Since then Slandering and Mis-repreſentation will not do, the Gentleman proceeds in the next place (<hi>Pag.</hi> 7.) <hi>to Wheedling;</hi> but the beſt on't is, he hath made a Rod for his own Britch, and his own Words reflect more upon his own Church than ours; for <hi>is it not a delicate innocent Church, that cannot be ſafe but in a fortified place? It is a great Argument of her modesty, to own her ſelf weak and unable to ſubſist without a Law to burn Hereticks;</hi> or what is worſe, to clap them up, and <hi>ſtifle them,</hi> or <hi>ſtarve them,</hi> or <hi>wrack them to death</hi> in the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> who cannot conform to all their Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions. <hi>Prayer, Faſting, Mortification of the Fleſh, and other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities are not, it ſeems, ſo proper means to remove her Fears and Jealouſies, but She muſt have a Coercive Power even over Kings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, The Primitive Chriſtians flouriſhed for three hundred years
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96337:6"/>under Perſecution,</hi> but yet their number increaſed more in three years in <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s Reign, than almoſt in all the three hundred years before. <hi>If this Church be from God it will-ſtand; hath not the Apoſtolical Church,</hi> (nay, the only Catholick Church, as <hi>Rome</hi> ſtiles it ſelf) <hi>the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, who is to continue with the true Church till the end of the World?</hi> Why then doth not She, who pretends to be the Mother-Church, of all others, ſet her Children an Example in the diſcarding her Sanguinary Laws againſt all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, and granting a full Liberty of Conſcience to all ſorts of Men? If She would do this, by her Succeſs therein, we ſhould the better judge the Expediency of it for our ſelves; if She will not do this, and afford Proteſtants Places of Profit and Honour, why ſhould we take off our Laws for their Sakes, who will abate nothing for ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. He acts the Divine, and would fain urge <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a probable Doctrine, becauſe of the many Wiſe and Learned that believe it,</hi> or at leaſt pretend to do ſo: By the ſame Argument he might as well prove Mahometiſm to be a probable Opinion; for there are many Wiſe Men, nay, ſome Learned men amongſt the Turks as well as amongſt the Papiſts. Whom he reflects upon by his <hi>new Tenet, which makes it Idolatry to adore the Divine Body of Chirſt; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be a Tranſubſtantiation or not,</hi> I am not able to judge, for I aſſure him this is the firſt time I ever heard of this Opinion: It cannot be the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s <hi>(nor the infallible Parliaments)</hi> as he calls it, for the Reaſon that is given by our <hi>Rubrick,</hi> is becauſe <hi>the Sacramental Bread and Wine remain ſtill in their very natural Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and therefore may not be adored,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the laſt Place, he proceeds to give us Advice, but the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Enemies is always dangerous to be taken, and ſurely none more dangerous than this, <hi>viz. That the Loyal Church of</hi> England <hi>ſhould change her old Principles of Loyalty, and learn of her Catholick Neighbours how to behave her ſelf towards Princes.</hi> What Principles would he have us change, and for what? Would he have us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce our conſtant Principle <hi>of Non-reſiſtance to Princes,</hi> and change it for that <hi>of the depoſing Doctrine?</hi> Would he have us learn of our Neighbour-catholicks how to make <hi>Holy Leagues</hi> againſt our King, and to <hi>murder</hi> our Royal Maſters? but he proceeds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Or She muſt give his Majeſty leave not to nouriſh a Snake in his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but to withdraw his Protection from ſuch as withdraw their Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96337:7"/>
            <p>This part of his Advice we are ready to take, for we are not for reſtraining of Princes, nor would we deſire him <hi>to nouriſh Snakes in his own Boſome,</hi> ſuch <hi>Raviliacks</hi> and <hi>Jaques Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> (I mean) who carry a mortal Sting full of deadly Poyſon againſt Princes, even in their very Principles, and have always ſhown it upon all opportunities in their Actions. Neither are we againſt his <hi>withdrawing his Protection from ſuch as ceaſe to be Loyal;</hi> nor are we for his protecting ſuch as never were ſo, ſuch as his Wiſe and Learned Grand-father, <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, ſaid, <hi>were never to be obliged by Benefits.</hi> May his Majeſty find his new Friends and Converts, that he hath endeavour'd ſo highly to oblige by his Toleration, to be as True and Loyal to him as his old Friends of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are, and always were; and may God Almighty preſerve him to protect all his Subjects, and then we ſhall not regard the grinning Threatnings, and ſnarling Inſinuations of any ſcribling Animals.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96337:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
